There we go.
All right.
Over to you, Sebastian.
You're still needed.
Yeah.
Classical.
You can see my slides.
Yes. Perfect.
Yeah. Hello.
Thank you for invitation
and for this absolutely great panel.
I would like to explore a question
that sits
at the intersection of philosophy,
literature, media theory, and digital art.
So all the things we have to do
in the l'o.
And the main question is
what happens to philosophy
when it's no longer
primarily written as a linear text?
And of course, electronic literature forms
a reflection
that are procedural, participatory
and non-linear.
And rather than guiding readers
through a single argument, they invite
navigation, choice, explanation,
and sometimes even collaboration.
So, I have to switch a little bit
because I have to many windows here.
I have only one window.
That's sometimes.
Yes, that's my agenda.
So I would begin with rhythm
thinking or classical philosophy filing.
And then I, connect philosophy
to other media forms.
And then I, have the question
or the idea of a transmedia hypertext.
So, to the classical way,
of course, when we look to the,
to the phenomenal Logic of Spirit
by Hegel,
we have at least
a highly intentional structure.
Each chapter prepares the reader
for the next, and the sequence matters
because the argument
unfolds dialectically.
And if we miss a stage, it weakens
one understanding
of the subsequent stages.
So a typical philosophy classes,
we begin with the first pages,
and in the end of the master we are
if it's good in on page four 550.
So, but, that's important to understand
the whole structure of the phenomenon,
phenomenology. And,
we have some kind of spiral.
It's it's a linear, but it's a spiral.
So that's in the dialectic
thinking new thing.
And, the author has constructed a path
and the reader follows it.
So, of course, the movement is active,
but it's largely guided by the author.
So of course
we can have fun with dialectics.
That's,
The spiral.
And that's a fun
picture of dialectic to dialectic.
We don't have to understand this now,
but it makes fun to look at.
And, of course,
this connects us
to the rhythm thing, thinking. And,
the question of in which way we could
philosophy phi in arithmetic form.
I think the most of,
you know, A Thousand Plateaus,
where the concept of
the resume is introduced.
And unlike a tree,
which has roots, branches and clearer key
resume spreads horizontally, and,
it has multiple entry points, every point
can potentially connect
to every other point.
And of course, knowledge
does not always proceed from foundation
toward conclusions.
It can emerge through connections, detours
and counters and unexpected associations.
And of course, this understanding
transforms reading.
And this, connects us to hypertext
because hypertext changes
this relationship.
And instead of moving page after page,
along a predetermined
route, readers choose links, open
nodes, return to earlier section,
skip entire branches, and are able
to understand the whole concept.
So, yes,
we're seeing your presenter notes
and not the presentation, the slideshow.
Okay.
Can you it's difficult for some of the
for us to see.
There you go. Good.
Got it.
All right.
Then I.
Yes. So,
So this also connects
us to the postmodern condition.
Because, Jean-Francois Lyotard
famously argued that modernity
relied on what he called grand narratives.
And he said
we should have a new form of philosophy
also, we skip totalizing philosophy.
And, he also, Yeah,
made it practice in 1985,
later collaborated with Terry Chapel
on the exhibition Lee material
at the Center
Pompidou in Paris and visited.
Visitors there did not move through
a clearly ordered sequence.
Instead, they navigated an environment
of multiple pathways
fragmented information, sounds,
images and texts.
There was no privileged route
through the exhibition,
and the medium embodied
the philosophical claim.
Meaning emerged through movement
and connection rather than through
hierarchical structure.
And we can see this
because it was reproduced online in,
I think, two years before,
so we can look,
this yeah,
this installation,
this exhibition as a blueprint.
And that's, connects me to blueprints.
I, I have no,
it's my favorite game at the moment,
and I completed its
it last week,
so I had to put a picture here,
but of course, we have, also,
this form of thinking
through choosing a path, a path,
thinking through it, with,
without only reading it.
And, this connects us also to,
of course, David Kolb.
I think you all new Socrates
in the labyrinth,
which was published in the 1990s.
And, of course, this also addresses
the idea of philosophy as, as hypertext.
And Cobb created
interconnected textual fragments
linked through multiple
pathways, and readers could move between
themes, arguments, and concepts
in different sequences.
Of course the medium changes, but
the material itself reminds philosophical
readers a counter arguments, conceptual
distinctions, and theoretical reflection.
So the hypertext structure
enriches philosophy,
but it's also connected
to philosophical writing.
So for me.
Occupies a middle position.
He need the fully embraces places
traditional linearity
or abandons textual argumentation
altogether.
So Socrates in the labyrinth
feels somewhat
like wandering through a library
whose books are connected by invisible
pathways, and one discovers unexpected.
I associate, but one is still engaged
in the world in the work.
Cobb therefore demonstrates
what hypertext can challenge,
and in which way it can challenge
the traditional structures.
And, yeah, now I,
connect this to,
to the question of,
yeah.
Media or intermedia philosophy.
There is this film by Pier Paolo
Pasolini, theory from 1968.
And it, it the the
the film isn't a philosophical tree
tries it's a firm.
And of course
there are philosophical questions
concerning desire, alienation,
transcendence and social order.
But at least we have no theory
which is presented as an argument.
So the film does not explain itself
conceptually,
but the medium itself becomes a vehicle.
So, and that also connects me
to Andrew sees Homestuck,
and Rosie,
there is a nice picture
which tries to connect
all the dimensions in in this text
because, Homestuck was published
between 1909 and 2060,
so seven years,
and it combines comics, animations, games,
hyperlinks, reader participation,
and extensive network storytelling.
Hypertext characters
not merely technical,
the were constantly reflects
on its own structure,
and It examines branching
timelines, L2 net
native possibilities, recursive
narratives, and interconnected realities.
So this is awesome.
And in the same time,
it presents a theory of hypertext
through hypertext itself,
but in the form of intermediate hypertext.
And that's quite interesting for me.
So we have here
all the examples I talked about.
And I
would say while Kolb remains
committed to argument
puzzle commits,
the audiovisual philosophy
or the audiovisual philosophical
narrative,
Homestuck commits, the philosophy
to procedural and networked structures.
And the difference is in this
also crucial but the philosophical
dimension is increasingly embedded
within a static experience.
So, instead discussing ideas externally.
The artwork performs them internally.
And this is where digital philosophy,
from my opinion,
becomes particularly interesting,
because the work no longer
merely communicates concepts, it
generates experiences.
So and in generating experiences,
I have a concept
for a transmedia hypertext,
and imagining a project consisting
of written philosophical fragments,
interactive digital environments,
audio visual sequences, fiction
narratives, emotional
and autobiographical elements,
and perhaps collaborative contributions.
And rather than existing as a single text,
philosophy would emerge through movement
between media.
Readers could become navigators
and interpretation would occur
through explanation.
It's clear that,
there are advantages and disadvantages.
So we have a greater reader involvement,
rich experi experiential dimensions.
We can integrate effect and cognition,
and we have complex X.
We can explore complex networked ideas
at the same time.
Philosophical rigor
can may become difficult to maintain.
Interpretations
may become fragmented, important arguments
may disappear behind esthetic effects.
But I do think philosophers will need to
collaborate with designers, artists
and developers and the audience.
Of course, the creation of digital
philosophy may become a collective process
rather than one, and that drives us
back to the material.
Thank you.
All right.
Great.
Thank you to Sebastian.
And thank you to all of our speakers.
We do have some time now
for questions and discussion.
So please, if if everyone will
let's see.
You can raise your hand.
You can post your question in the chat.
You can wave madly at me
like a blow up doll at the car dealership.
I will take any such movement
toward asking questions
or offering comments.
Anyone?
Am I seeing a hand up from.
Maybe not.
All right, I'm interested.
And this is kind of I'm going
to throw this out here for everybody.
So apologies if this is out there.
I'm not a philosophy person.
So there's a couple of you who've touched
on philosophy and those sorts of threads.
But I'm constantly
sort of thinking about that.
You know, we come back to this idea
of a labyrinth and,
and that it's, you know, that it's
sort of a
nonhierarchical expression
of how we think about
sometimes hypertext and digital pieces.
But interestingly to me, a labyrinth
in its purest form is one path
with many turns.
Labyrinth
is meant to be explored
by not even explored,
but traveled by a penitent
who is often on their knees
working their way around the path
for to, you know,
express their devotion to, to
some sort of form of worship
or meditation.
How does this align with
hypertext works as we as we know them
and how we think of them?
Can we can
we reconcile that sort of concept
with the structures that we work with,
whether it's AI
or it's hypertext
or it's transmedia or even.
Sort of
works that speak to other previous works.
Our contact works, as it were.
Anyone?
Should I begin?
Go for it?
Yeah.
I think you are totally right.
A labyrinth is,
You can.
It's not linear
in a way that you are not able to go back.
Or sometimes there are two ways
to different ways,
but at least there is only one goal.
And if you have bad luck,
there's a monitor there.
And tries you in directions
you don't want to.
So I, I would say the labyrinth is we,
we should
that's the reason why I think there is
some is a better,
better way
to have a metaphor for hypertext.
Because it's more than one, linear
path.
And it,
it hasn't a hierarchical structure.
Excellent.
Thank you. Anyone else?
Thoughts?
Questions?
Answers?
Maybe. Just a thought.
So I was taking notes
during all the other presentations.
I think lots of interesting connections
between all of them.
And I think this helps to,
to make some of those connections because,
I mean, in 249,
you've got this massive archive
of fragments of stories,
but what you're actually doing
as the player
is putting it all back together
and making those connections.
And by the end, what you need to do
is trace back where the ideas came from
that led to the
the machine being able to alter reality
and then just cut those links.
So you're actually
rising it and figuring out, okay, which
where did the idea come from?
What did it lead to,
and then how far back do I need
to go to stop this idea existing?
So I think that sort of reflects
the way that we do linearize things.
Even when you're going through
a hypertext,
you take a path through the hypertext,
and if you go take a different path,
you backtrack and then you go,
so it's like, I mean, like Sebastian
was going through a labyrinth,
you've got to go a certain way
and then you can go a different way, but
you can only be going
one way at a time. Right?
So we are,
I think, going through time linearly
and we have to move through space
linearly as well.
So yeah,
I think there's something interesting
about the fact
that we tend to linearize things.
So even though, Sebastian, you're talking
about philosophy being all results,
as you go
through and think through the arguments,
you are imposing a linear path through it,
I think.
But everyone might have a different path.
I guess that's what's interesting.
Great.
Just a thought.
Excellent.
Any other
comments? Questions?
We've been very quiet.
Maybe everyone's still waking up.
Those of you in more western time zones.
I have a question to Alex.
Go for it.
Because, the machine is changing.
You, because you you quote this,
that, some characters as this is it.
Yeah.
That's really interesting because, some
I connect
sometimes changing to also subjectivity.
Would you connect this also is the machine
has the machine I identity
which is also connecting it
to it's dangerous
to to Yeah.
To feed the machine.
I think so.
Yeah.
So I mean the,
the archive that you're exploring,
I didn't manage to see all of it,
so I probably missed some of the details.
And it is quite I mean, it's like 100
and something years of history
and lots of different characters.
But but yeah, I think what's interesting
is that the machine you discover
towards the end that
actually you are the machine or you're
the algorithm running in the machine.
So when this character Liam,
who talks about the the machine devouring
books and everything,
he's talking to Abbie, but Abbie is
what stands for as algorithmic
something, something interface.
Right.
So it's actually a it's an acronym
for the algorithm.
And yeah, it's partly dangerous, I think,
because that seems to be conscious
and seems to be sentient.
Right.
And part of the process
of destroying the machine.
One of the endings, actually,
Abbie is still there, but Abbie is just
like a dead chatbot that doesn't actually
have any personality anymore.
So I think, yeah,
maybe it's suggesting
that something about that personality,
that that's what's dangerous about it.
And maybe that's also connects to people's
fears about AI becoming sentient.
And that somehow is dangerous.
Anyway,
I'm rambling,
but that's something like that.
And that somewhat connects
to what you're asking.
Could I ask a question?
Of course, Stephanie, go for it.
So you seem to suggest
that the all the different
histories of.
Visual or design possibilities,
or to take on
at least to encounter
some kind of esthetics expressions.
And is that correct?
Is that what you were suggesting?
Yes, yes.
It's what makes you think
that those things can talk to each other.
I mean, they can bump into each other
and the person
and has always been the case,
the person who wants to make
a film of a story or something,
do you know what I mean?
They they will in their own mind.
They will modulate to do that.
But I don't see
that it changes the actual,
you know,
written texts of whoever Hegel, you know,
to have been treated that way,
or in fact,
that any written text can be treated
that way.
But what does it do to it, if anything?
Yeah, I understand what you mean,
but I, I see, similarities to,
we have books.
We have, of course, books
don't change through,
electronic literature.
So it's added to to the box.
And,
I would see the same to some kind of,
intermediate hypertext philosophy.
It it won't, with,
has influence
on our contemporary philosophy,
but it it wouldn't change
the classical philosophy, the,
the written philosophy.
And I would also say that
written philosophy is, is,
is quite important.
But at least when we look,
I'm a media philosopher,
we have I have also with students
sometimes problems in understanding
what is the philosophical concept
in a movie or in a video game.
And I, I think, such a structure
can help.
Think through also the,
the visuals, also the images, without
because I think then written text
sometimes lag because we have to
a translation process,
we translate a movie
to a written text to a argument.
And, I want to try to figure out,
is it possible to argue
through pictures,
through through images or through videos,
but how does that relate to
to to translating
through languages, don't you
do you feel that the video or whatever?
Totally right.
It's similar to translating
through languages, of course,
and in fact a visual.
It will affect the French thing
differently
than it will affect the,
you know, Swahili thing and so forth.
Right?
I mean, so it's an unending
creation of things.
The question is, does it
does that eat in Alex's terms,
all the written stuff
that it started from?
I wouldn't say so.
I would say, no, it doesn't eat.
But maybe we can, understand different,
more visual cultures
through this form of thinking.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you all so very much